In this lecture, we're going to explore model context protocol or MCP.
So now let's start with something more basic, what is MCP and what is the problem it is trying to
solve. So MCP refers to model context protocol and model here is the large language model
that you use to build your AI application. Context here refers to let's say you build an HR
chatbot application and to answer the employee query, it needs access to certain enterprise HR
data or third-party data. So when you retrieve the data and provide it to the large language model,
you provide it some context. And then finally we have the protocol and we know protocol means
certain sort of rules which allow you to exchange data between two devices. And in this case,
we are exchanging data between the large language model or the model and different data sources
whether internal or external. So MCP is an open protocol that standardizes how applications provide
context to LLMs. So in summary, you have the LLM and you have the data sources and you provide
data to the LLM using some protocol. Now what is the problem that MCP is trying to solve?
So first, it solves the M multiplied by N custom integration problem. So let's say within your
enterprise, you have three different applications, AIAP 1, AIAP 2 and AIAP 3. And each of these
apps needs data access from three different data sources within the enterprise. One is the database,
document repository and API service. So what you will do is let's say in case of if you're using AWS,
so you're going to write custom integration problem using a lambda function where you will write
some custom code for AIAP 1 to access data from this database. Then from document repository,
then from API service, similarly you will do for app to where you will access the database,
document repo and API service, similarly for app 3. So you will have to write code for these three
integrations, then these three a total of nine integrations. So now if you use MCP, what happens is
you can connect all the apps you have within your enterprise to this MCP client and then this MCP
client connects one to one with this MCP server which connects to these three data sources. So you will
have three plus three, six implementations. So we'll reduce the number of integration points and we'll
discuss in a little bit what this client and server means and how this actually works. But just
for now, remember that the number of integrations have been reduced. Next, it also standardizes how
LLM access data from different data sources and we're going to discuss about this in a little bit.
But right now, AWS offers more than 50 plus MCP servers. Now let's go and try and understand
how MCP actually works through a use case. Now let's say we are trying to build a hotel booking
AI application using MCP. Now through this example, we're going to understand five core components
of MCP host client MCP server transport layer and tools resources and props. So let's say for our
hotel booking AI application, there are two main backend data sources. One, we have a PDF document
in an S3 bucket, which is all the hotel room features, what kind of bed it has, whether it has a TV
or not and so on. And second, we have a DynamoDB where we have stored all the hotel room inventory,
which an end user can query. And then we have some tools. Let's say we have bedrock knowledge
basis. We know better knowledge is a managed rack solution from AWS and we've created one instance
of bedrock knowledge base, which is KB ID is equal to one, two, three. And then we have also written
a lambda function, which is able to retrieve the data from this hotel room inventory table.
Now we have these two backend data sources and we have two tools. Now let's say we have a user
Joe and he poses a question to this hotel booking AI application asking for hotel room features,
which are stored in this PDF in this S3 bucket. Now this request from the user is going to go
to something known as host and host is basically just any AI application that uses a large
language model. And in this use case, it could simply be a chatbot through which this end user
is interacting with the application. But since MCP is being used a lot by the coding AI agents,
so some of the other hosts could be simply like VS code, maybe a chatbot as we discussed
or any AI app. Once the request is sent to the host, it will redirect it to the large language
model and in case of AWS, it might go to Amazon bedrock and then whichever model that you select,
whether it's cloud or Titan, no, pro and so on. Now here mostly you're going to use
converse API. Now if you have not used bedrock converse API, it's very similar to the invoke model
API, but additionally it allows you to send the tools details to the large language model. So if
you see here the converse API while making the request, you define the model ID. So we are using
entropic here, then we are passing the message, which is basically the user query. And then we are
also telling the model which are the tools available for this model. And here you can define the
tool configuration. So essentially what we are doing here is we're sending the user prompt
and along with that, we are also sending through a prompt template, what are the tool options
available for the LLM to use. And in this case, these are the tools that are available for
LLM to get context. So what bedrock is going to do is, along with this user request and the tool
configuration data that has been sent, it will request to use this tool that we have here
bedrock knowledge basis with KBID 123. Now this request, the large language model would send to
something known as client in MCP terms. And if you can see here, client, client is embedded in
this host. So we discussed host could be a chatbot or it could be ID like VS code in case of
coding AI agents. And this client maintains one to one connection with MCP server. And we're going
to talk about MCP server in a bit. Now what are these clients? So you might have heard about
client or Amazon QCLI, Windsor, Claude desktop. These are all the clients that MCP supports at this point
of time. And you can install all of these clients in your ID or VS code. And that's why I've written
here that this client can be embedded in the host. And you can also have multiple clients in the
same host. Okay. Next concept that we have is servers. So we have the MCP servers. And we have,
in this case, AWS MCP server for bedrock knowledge basis and AWS Lambda MCP servers. So what are
servers? Servers are lightweight programs that expose specific capabilities in a standardized format.
So these MCP servers are lightweight programs that have been built by AWS. And in most scenarios,
the MCP servers are built by the tool or service providers. And once these servers are built,
there are two ways in which you can deploy these AWS MCP servers or any other service provided by
different tool service providers. One is sometimes known as a remote. And it's a more recent
phenomenon where it's a managed service. And let's say in AWS case, it will be deployed
somewhere in the AWS environment. The second and most common one is local system or Docker
deployment, where you deploy the server on your laptop itself. And most of the servers
available by AWS are available to be deployed locally on your system or laptop. So if you go to
this link, AWS lab start, GitHub.io, you can see all the servers that are available from AWS. And
you can see in different categories. So you have AWS MCP server, knowledge base MCP server,
then for infrastructure, you have CDK cloud formation, Terraform. And for AML, you have Amazon
bedrock, knowledge bases, and then you have missing cube business. And then in the data analytics
space, you have for DynamoDB, Elasticsearch, and whole bunch of others. Then you have a cost
operations, developer tools, and you can see there are more than 50 plus servers. And you can
search each of them from here from category, workflows, name, and so on. So once this large language
model requests, the client to go and retrieve contextual data from these backend sources,
using this tool, use kb_id123, which is for this particular knowledge base, it's going to
translate this request into an MCP protocol format. And we'll discuss about what is MCP protocol
format in a bit. So now this client makes a request to the server using JSON RPC. And then this
MCP server is going to retrieve the data from the backend using these tools. And it's going to
send a response back to the client. And this client is going to send the tool, use, or contextual
data to the LLM, and then LLM along with that context. And its intrinsic knowledge is going to send
a final response back. And in this case, it's going to send a room detail that it has
retrieved from here to the end user. Now let's just understand a couple of things more
for this MCP protocol, how this actually works. Now if you look at the fourth component,
we have the transport layer, where there's a communication between the client and server. So you
can see here, the client and server are exchanging information. And for this, you need to keep in mind
two things. One, so you have the data layer. And here we use the JSON RPC. So we use the JSON data
format to exchange data. And then at the transport layer, you have two options. One, we have the
standard input output called as SDDI until very recently we only had this option. And this is mainly
used when you're deploying the MCP server on your local system. Now for the remote managed servers,
which are deployed, let's say within an AWS environment, you will use the HTTP protocol.
And then finally, we have the fifth component, tools, resources and prompts. Now let's quickly
try to understand what these three stand for. So first, we have the tools. And these are basically
nothing but functions that LLMs can call to retrieve data. And these are the two tools we had
in our case. And from the MCP protocol perspective, it's mandatory for these MCP servers
to detail out to the client what are all the tools or basically API calls that are available
with this server. Next, we have the resources and resources are nothing but actual data,
which might be in a database or in file system, which can be used by the model as context. So it's
the actual data that is retrieved using the tools. And then finally, we have the prompts and prompts
are template that guide how models interact with the tools. So in this scenario, if we look at
here, we have a prompt template, which includes the user request or the prompt, then defines
which large language model we're going to use. And finally, also what are the tools available
like what we had here for large language model to use. Okay, so that's pretty much it from this
lecture. I'll see you in the next lecture. Thank you.